<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "Development_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="chap-Development_Guide-Install_Chapter">
  <title>Platypus Application Designer</title>
  <para>The application designer software package is included into the developer&apos;s kit and can be bundled with the Platypus Platform runtime installation.</para>
  <para>The developer&apos;s kit may be supplied:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>on a CD/DVD</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>as an installer archive which can be downloaded from the Internet.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>If the developer&apos;s kit is supplied as an archive, unpack its contents  to the  folder of your choice on the hard drive.</para>
  <note>
    <para>Platypus Platform runtime installation instructions are provided in the Administration Guide.</para>
  </note>
  <section id="sect-Administration_Guide-Install_Chapter-Test_Section_1">
    <title>System requirements </title>
    <para>System requirements for installing the developer&apos;s kit on a computer includes:
   <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>32-bit (x86) or 64-bit (x64) CPU, 1 GHz or above</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>2 GB (for 32-bit system) or 3 GB (for 64-bit system) RAM</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>10 GB of free disk space</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Operating system with  graphical user interface: Windows or Linux</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Oracle JDK 7</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Internet access for  updates downloading</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Installation guide</title>
    <para>
To install the developer&apos;s kit, perform the following actions:<orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Launch the   <filename>platypusdesigner-windows.exe</filename> file for  Windows OS or <filename>platypusdesigner-linux.sh</filename> for Linux.</para>
          <note>
            <para>For Linux OS, the user must have  access rights enabling to launch the executable file. </para>
          </note>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
Click  <guibutton>Next</guibutton> to proceed to the next installation step.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para> Read licensing terms and conditions; check the <guilabel>I accept the terms of the license agreement</guilabel> option to accept; click <guibutton>Next</guibutton> to proceed to the next step.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
Select the applications installation directory and options for creating  shortcuts on the desktop and in the installed programs menu; click <guibutton>Next</guibutton> to proceed to the next step.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
Click <guibutton>Install</guibutton> to begin the  <application>Platypus Application Designer</application> installation process. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
After the installation process is finished, click  <guibutton>Finish</guibutton>; check the <guilabel>Launch Platypus application designer after the installer closes</guilabel> option to launch the designer.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
  </para>
    <note>
      <para>Specify the path to the  JDK in the <parameter>jdkhome</parameter> parameter in the <application>Platypus Application Designer</application> configuration file at <filename>platypusdesigner/etc/platypusdesigner.conf</filename>, if the its installation location is other than default. Incorrect value of  the <parameter>jdkhome</parameter> parameter can lead to errors which may occur when launching the designer.</para>
    </note>
    <para>
To remove  Platypus Application Designer from you computer, perform the following actions:
   <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use the your OS standard mechanism of programs removal, as an alternative, use the  <filename>uninstall.exe</filename> program for Windows or  <filename>uninstall.sh</filename> for Linux from the   installation directory.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Confirm the  components removal by clicking  <guibutton>Finish</guibutton> button; if necessary, select the option of removing  configuration data from the user&apos;s directory.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
  </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Configuration tips</title>
    <para><application>Platypus Application Designer</application> supports  localization of  menus, messages texts, etc. Currently,  the following languages are supported:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>English</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Russian</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>The localization language is selected automatically when you launch the application designer according to  the regional settings of the operating system.</para>
    <para>To force the change of the localization language: </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Edit the <application>Platypus Application Designer</application> configuration file — append the  <parameter>default_options</parameter> parameter with the  <option>--locale ru:RU</option> or <option>--locale en:US</option> option.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Restart the application designer.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>You can also change the application designer localization language by adding the <option>--locale ru:RU</option> or <option>--locale en:US</option> option to the command line for launching the  <application>Platypus Application Designer</application>.</para>
    <para>Platypus Application Designer supports connection of the various user interface Look and Feel  (LaF). There are LaFs for specific operating systems, universal styles  (<literal>Metal</literal> and <literal>Nimbus</literal>), and LaFs which can be supplied by  third-party developers.</para>
    <para>To change the  <application>Application Designer</application> LaF:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Edit the designer configuration file — append the  <parameter>default_options</parameter> parameter with the  <option>--laf <replaceable>LaF</replaceable></option> option, where <replaceable>LaF</replaceable> corresponds to the name of LaF or full name of the LaF class. If the third-party LaF is used, it is also necessary to include the style library into the path which can be accessed by the <application>Application Designer</application> classloader.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Restart the application designer.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Runtime environment setup</title>
    <para>The Platypus Platform runtime is required  to start, debug and deploy applications. You must specify the path to the runtime directory for the Platypus Application Designer to be able to run and debug your applications.</para>
    <para>Specify the location of the Platypus Platform runtime directory in the computer&apos;s file system:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select   <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Platypus Platform</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice> in the main menu.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>In the selection dialog, specify  path to the Platypus Platform directory.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Add the J2EE server instance which can be used to launch the Platypus application:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>In the <guilabel>Services</guilabel> window of the <guilabel>Servers</guilabel> node context menu select the <guimenuitem>Add server...</guimenuitem> item.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>In the J2EE server adding wizard, select the server type, server name, and specify its preferences: path to the server directory, administrator&apos;s login and password.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <note>
      <para>The current version of Platypus Application Designer supports launching of applications in  Apache Tomcat 7. Download Apache Tomcat 7 from the developer&apos;s site and unpack it in the directory of your choice on your hard drive.</para>
    </note>
  </section>
</chapter>
