<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. --><!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "Administration_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="chapter_installation">
  <title>Platform&apos;s installation</title>
  <para>If the Platypus Platform runtime is delivered as a ZIP file, unpack its contents to a location according to your preference on your hard drive.</para>
  <note>
    <para>Instructions for installing the <application>Platypus Application Designer</application> developer tool are available in the Development Guide.</para>
  </note>
  <section id="install-requirements">
    <title>System requirements</title>
    <para>
Below you can see prerequisites for launching the platform components on your computer:
   <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>32-bit (x86) or 64-bit (x64) processor running at 1 gigahertz (GHz) or higher </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>1 gigabyte (GB) (for 32-bit system) or 2 GB (for 64-bit system) RAM</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>5 gigabytes (GB) of free hard disk space </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Windows, Linux, Mac OS X or other operating system like Unix </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Oracle JRE 7 or OpenJDK 7 </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Graphical user interface for client operation</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Internet access for downloading updates and working with external mapping service (In a corporate network, Internet access may be arranged through a proxy server.)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Google Chrome 19, Mozilla Firefox 10, Internet Explorer 9 or newer versions of browsers for Platypus client HTML5 operation</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>  </para>
    <para>The Platypus Platform supports the following database servers: </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Oracle Database 10g and higher</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>IBM DB2 9 and higher</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Microsoft SQL Server 2008 and higher</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>MySQL (InnoDB) 5.5 and higher</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>PostgreSQL 9 and higher</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>H2 Database 1.3 and higher</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>For information on installing and configuring the database server, refer to the relevant installation and administration manuals, provided by database server manufacturers.</para>
    <para>The platform runtime is supplied with the H2 database. This database  does not require any additional installation and configuration steps.</para>
    <para>For running applicatons on server side in a J2EE servlet container use a  J2EE server or container, for example:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Apache Tomcat 7</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Glassfish 3.1.2</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>JBoss AS7</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>For information on installing and configuring the servlet container or J2EE server, refer to the relevant installation and administration manuals, provided by their manufacturers.</para>
  </section>
  <section id="install-guide">
    <title>Installation guide</title>
    <para> To install the platform components, perform the following actions:<orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Go to the <filename>install</filename> subdirectory of the Platypus distribution kit.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Run  <filename>install.bat</filename> files for the Windows OS or perform the  <command>sh install.sh</command> command for Linux.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Select the language of the installation program user interface.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Select the installation directory.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Select components to be installed. </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>The platform&apos;s core components (required)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Java SE desktop client</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Geospacial and maps components</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Components required for operation of the standalone application server and  in  J2EE servlet containers and on the application servers</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Components required for operation with COM/DCOM and OPC servers</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Select settings of shortcuts for running the Platypus client in your system environment. </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
  </para>
    <para>After installation, the platform&apos;s directory will have the following structure:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><filename>platypus/</filename></para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><filename>bin/</filename></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><filename>lib/</filename></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><filename>etc/</filename></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><filename>run/</filename></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><filename>logs/</filename></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section id="install-uninstall">
    <title>Uninstallation guide</title>
    <para>
To delete the platform components from your computer, perform the following actions:
   <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Select the  <application>UninstallPlatypus</application> menu item from the installed programs menu. For Windows, use the conventional mechanism for removing programs.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Confirm uninstalling of Platypus components. If necessary, enable an option for removing the working directory.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
