<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. --><!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "Administration_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="chap-Administration_Guide-Server_Chapter">
  <title>Platypus Application Server</title>
  <para>The main purpose of use of  the Platypus Application Server is to provide support for  various binary communication protocols. </para>
  <section id="sect-Administration_Guide-Server_Chapter-Test_Section_2">
    <title>Running server</title>
    <para>To start the server application, you  run the startup script for the server, located in the
    <filename>/run</filename> folder:    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><filename>server.bat</filename> is the script file to start the  server in Windows. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><filename>server.sh</filename> is the script file to start the server in Linux.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>For running the server in production environment, it is recommended to configure it as an operating system service.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Command line options</title>
    <para>To configure running of the Platypus server, edit the contents of the startup script files.</para>
    <para>The command for running the server is as follows:</para>
    <programlisting>java <replaceable>JVM_OPTIONS</replaceable> -cp Server.jar;<replaceable>EXT_CLASSPATH</replaceable> com.eas.server.ServerMain <replaceable>OPTIONS</replaceable></programlisting>
    <para>where <replaceable>JVM_OPTIONS</replaceable> is Java Virtual Machine options, <replaceable>EXT_CLASSPATH</replaceable> are paths to be added to the Java class loader search path, <replaceable>OPTIONS</replaceable> are server application running parameters.</para>
    <table>
      <title>Command line options</title>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry align="center">Parameter</entry>
            <entry align="center">Description</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <parameter>applicationpath APP_PATH</parameter>
            </entry>
            <entry>Path to the folder, which contains the application. If this parameter is specified, the application will be started from this drive folder, otherwise the application will be started from the database. This option has a short ap synonym.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <parameter>-url JDBC_URL</parameter>
            </entry>
            <entry>URL of the connection to the database in the JDBC format.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <parameter>-dbuser DB_USER</parameter>
            </entry>
            <entry>Username for authorization in the database.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <parameter>-dbpassword DB_PASSWORD</parameter>
            </entry>
            <entry>User password for authorization in the database.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <parameter>-dbschema DB_SCHEMA</parameter>
            </entry>
            <entry>Database scheme.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><parameter>-iface</parameter><replaceable> ADRESS:PORT</replaceable>,<replaceable>ADRESS:PORT</replaceable></entry>
            <entry>Network interfaces and listening ports for the server.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <parameter>-protocols</parameter>
              <replaceable> PORT:PROTOCOL,PORT:PROTOCOL</replaceable>
            </entry>
            <entry>Network protocols for listening ports.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <parameter>-loglevel LOG_LEVEL</parameter>
            </entry>
            <entry>Logging level. This parameter specifies the minimum level, which will be shown in the log. For the description of logging levels, see Appendix A.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <parameter>-log LOG_FILE_PATH</parameter>
            </entry>
            <entry>Name and path of the log file.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <parameter>-tasks </parameter>
              <replaceable>MODULES_NAME</replaceable>
            </entry>
            <entry>The list of server modules (separated by comma without spaces) for processing incoming data and background tasks. The <methodname>received(data)</methodname>function should be defined for the incoming data processing module. The incoming data processing modules can have the <property>@stateless</property>annotation, or be without it. Background tasks modules should not have the <property>@stateless annotation. When starting server, modules with this annotation will be skipped.</property></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <para>Example of the Platypus application server running command:</para>
    <programlisting>java -cp Server.jar com.eas.server.ServerMain -url jdbc:oracle:thin:@serverHost:1521:adb -dbuser user1 -dbpassword secret -loglevel INFO -log serverlog.log -iface 0.0.0.0:8500 -protocols 8500:platypus</programlisting>
  </section>
</chapter>
